today we're going to build and deploy an
app using a stack I've been dying to
show you we are going to use Dino fresh
Dino deploy and Dino KV to build a
voting web app by the end of this video
you are going to be surprised at how
easy it is to build something with the
dino stack compared to using next JS
react and Versa before we start let's
first Define what all the parts of the
stack are and what they do created by
the same mind behind node.js Ryan though
Dino is a fairly new JavaScript
typescript and web assembly runtime
built on the rust programming language
that means that Vino is a rust program
that can understand and execute
typescript JavaScript and web assembly
code Lino is different from node.js in
many ways it has a more secure
permissions model and it does not have
npm install or note mode values Vino
also implements web platform apis which
means the learning curve is not that
high since we all have used these apis
on the browsers before it is basically
node.js if the creator of node.js could
go back in time and fix his mistakes
fresh is the next JS of the Dino World
it is a web framework with features like
server-side rendering API routes and all
that you would expect it does not use
react instead it uses react and it uses
something called Island based client
hydration that makes loading and
interaction times faster it requires no
configuration no building step and it
comes with typescript support out of the
box Vino deploy is a cloud service where
we can deploy JavaScript typescript and
webassembly apps with no config
whatsoever it's like the versel or
netflify of the Dino World Dino KV is a
key value database that can be used by
any Lino program that is deployed using
Dino deploy and because it's built on
Foundation DB it can handle millions of
operations per second it's currently on
beta but thankfully I've got an
invitation so we can try it out after
installing Dino using any of the many
methods of installation we are going to
run this command to create a new Fresh
project this will install fresh and is
going to ask us for the name of the
project if you want to use tailwind and
if we use vs code after we reply yes to
all of them we're going to open the
folder in our vs code there we are going
to delete all the boilerplate files the
installer has created for us and we are
going to create a file called
index.tsx inside of the route folder
fresh has the same routing idea as next
JS so if for example you create a file
called about that DSX inside of the
routes folder that page will be visible
on the slash about page of your website
we also have an Islands folder this is
where we are going to put our
interactive components in our index.tsx
page we will write down this code this
HTML code has a form with a method post
and three inputs one for a question and
two more for the options we are also
using the head component from fresh that
allows us to change the title from the
head to see what this looks like in the
browser we are going to run fresh by
going to our console and running the
Vino task start command then when we go
to localhost 8000 we will see a form
that looks like this as you can see when
we write down our question the options
and click on the button we get an error
we have to write the code to process the
submission of the form to process the
form we are going to write this code on
top of the home component inside of the
object called Handler there is a post
function that fresh will automatically
call when we submit the form inside of
it we are getting the value of the form
and responding to the user with the same
values to check that everything is
working how cool is this with did not
have to write any fetch code no event
listeners awesome to save the question
as well as the options on the database
we're going to extend the post Handler a
bit here we are creating an object
called payload that will hold all the
data of the question as well as the vote
counters that both start in zero we also
give it a random ID here is what it
would look like we are then calling the
dino KV database and we are saving the
question object into it as a string
using the random ID as a key then we are
redirecting the user to the URL slash
questions slash question ID that would
look something like this as you can see
it looks like the submission is working
because we are being redirected but that
URL is not found which makes sense since
we haven't created that page yet to
handle this URL we are going to create a
new file inside of the questions folder
and we're going to write this code here
we are using the Handler object again
but we are now writing a get function
inside of it this is a function that
will be called server side when the user
goes to that page on this function we
are looking for a question with the ID
that is on the URL that the user was
redirected to if we find it we will call
context that render with the question
from the database that data will be
passed down to the question component
where we will show the user an H1 with
the question they asked this is how the
page looks like after we refresh the
browser we are now going to create a
button that we can click to send and
record a vote on our database for this
we're going to create a new component on
the islands folder called
button.tsx the islands folder is where
we put the interactive components they
are the ones rendered on the client side
on the bottom Iceland we are going to
write this code this is a component that
receives some props like the question ID
the option text the amount of votes that
option has and then number of options it
is Option 1 or option two for
interactivity we use free acts to use a
signal which is similar to reacts use
State on the function on click which
will be called when we click the button
just for now we are changing the value
of the loading signal to true and after
a second and a half we are setting it
back to false we are also increasing the
number of the votes signal which has a
default value of the current number of
votes of the question we then import the
button component into our question
component and now our page looks like
this with interactivity and everything
to record votes on our database I would
like to get a URL like this one where we
will get the question ID the user is
voting on as well as which option they
chose for this we're going to create a
new file on our route folder there we
will write down this code let's go
through it part by part first we are
extracting the query parameters ID and
option and from the URL then we are
getting the question from the database
after that we are using json.parse to
turn that string into a JS object and
then we are updating that question using
KV that set if the option parameter on
the URL is one we are increasing the
value of the option 1 votes else we are
increasing number twos now all is left
is to make the bottom component send a
request to that endpoint now in the on
click function we are sending a fetch
post request to our API endpoint with a
question ID and the option parameters we
now should be able to click the buttons
and after we refresh the page the votes
count should come from the data base
deploying is incredibly easy after
logging into Vino deploy dashboard all
we have to do is select the GitHub repo
where the project is and it will all be
deployed automatically in a number of
seconds as you can see the app looks
great we can test it immediately and we
also get a suite admin panel where we
can see logs analytics and we can even
visualize the data in our Dino KV even
though it looks like it this video is
not sponsored by Dino I wish it was I am
just super super impressed by what the
Xenon team has built and I wanted to
share it with you it is also seamless
and easy to use that it takes no time to
build a functioning product that can be
scaled to millions of users thanks to
dino deploy fresh works like a charm the
waveforms are handled API routes
interactivity the developer experience
it is all really good as you saw I spent
zero time installing dependencies
configuring typescript Tailwind Etc
fresh has it all I really want to know
what you think so please write down on
the comments what your opinion is on
this video stack did you know it is this
cool have you built something with it
should I make a dino fresh deploy course
write what you think on the comments I
am going to be reading right now and
don't forget if you want to learn things
like JavaScript python react react
native go that flutter among many others
for absolutely free all you have to do
is click the link below you can join any
of our many free courses you can take
right now for absolutely free with me
click the link below and I will see you
there anjana comes see you on the next
one bye
foreign